Population Problems Collection, 1896-1979
Sophia Smith Collection
Population problems collection
1896-1979
MS 438
3 boxes, 4 volumes (2 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
The Population Problems Collection contains mainly printed materials on issues pertaining to world population problems in the 20th century; family planning and the birth control movement in the United States; the international birth control movement; and development programs and agencies that assist poorer women and their families. Related issues such as sterilization and eugenics are also documented. Types of materials include books, pamphlets, booklets, newspaper clippings, articles, and essays. Published books include: The Salon and the Royal Academy Booklet on Eugenics (1908); Proceedings of the International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the Family (1948); and Birth Control and the Americas, 1830-1970 (1974). The collection dates from 1896 to 1979, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1970s.
The Population Problems Collection contains mainly printed materials on issues pertaining to world population problems in the 20th century; family planning and the birth control movement in the United States; the international birth control movement; and development programs and agencies that assist poorer women and their families. Related issues such as sterilization and eugenics are also documented. Types of materials include books, pamphlets, booklets, newspaper clippings, articles, and essays. Published books include: The Salon and the Royal Academy Booklet on Eugenics (1908); Proceedings of the International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the Family (1948); and Birth Control and the Americas, 1830-1970 (1974). The collection dates from 1896 to 1979, with the bulk of the materials dating from the 1970s.
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Periodic additions to collection are expected and may not be reflected in this record.
Birth control--Developing countries--History--20th century--Sources; Birth control--Research--Sources; Birth control--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Eugenics--History--Sources; Population policy--History--20th century; Sophia Smith Collection
- Contents list (Box 1)
- Birth control, general
  - Bibliographies
    - "Bibliography of Family Planning and Population," Simon Population Trust, vols. 1-2 1972-73 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Miscellaneous 1927-81 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Articles 1941-78 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Clippings 1970-81 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Pamphlets 1905-81, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - "Birth Control Handbook," Medicine for the People 1972 (2 copies) (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials 1961-80 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Assessment of Need and Attitude of Birth Control and Family Planning Services in Hampshire County, Massachusetts January, 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Baum, Margaret: correspondence about Planned Parenthood and miscellaneous 1953-73 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- "Bellagio IV Population Conference," Working Papers1977 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Birth rates: clippings 1971-78 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Bradlaugh, Charles and Annie Besant, Fruits of Philosophy: A Treatise on the Population Question 1896 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Brook Advisory Centers: Annual Report 1970 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Center for Population Options: printed materials undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Cleary, Barbara, The Fight for Birth Control in America 1974 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Cowles, Elizabeth Bates, Birth Control Clinic, Des Moines, IA 1934-74 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- Day, Alice Taylor, "Persuasion or Coercion: Alternatives in Population Control" 1969 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Family Planning Digest, vol. I, no.6 Nov 1972 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- India
  - Sixth All India Conference on Family Planning: Report of the Proceedings 1968 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous printed materials 1970-74 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- International Planned Parenthood Federation: article and wall chart 1979, undated (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Ireland: clippings 1973 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Massachusetts Family Planning Consortium 1971-72 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- "Oral Contraceptives and the Walnut Creek Study Controversy," National Women's Health Network 1980 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Population: pamphlets 1949-78 (Box 3, Folder 1-2)
- Population Reference Bureau: pamphlets, mailings undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Sawyer, Annita P., "The Two-Child Family: A Look at the Future" 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- "The Human Population," Scientific AmericanSept 1974 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- Sterilization: articles, clippings, and correspondence 1971-2005 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- UNICEF and family planning: "The Woman Physician," vol. 25, no.9 Sept 1970 (Box 3, Folder 7)
- "Women in a Hungry World: A Study/Action Kit," World Hunger/Global Development Project (4 vols.) 1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- Zero Population Growth: pamphlets, periodical ("National Reporter"), and mailings 1971-79, undated (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- BOOKS ON SHELF
  - Proceedings of the International Congress on Population and World Resources in Relation to the Family 1948 (2 copies)
  - Reed, James Wesley. Birth Control and the Americans: 1830-1970 (2 vols.) 1974
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Second International Congress of Eugenics, Museum of Natural History, New York, NY: group photographSeptember 1921 (Map-case Flat file dwr 4)